Masshiro na keshiki ni ima sasowarete
Boku wa yuku yo mada minu sekai e
Maigo no mama tabi shiteita
nezumiiro no sora no shita
Higawari no chizu
ikutsumo no yume ga nijinde ita
Itsuka wa sa chippoke na
boku no kono hohaba demo
Ano kumo no mukou made yukeru kana
Tsuyogatte kizutsuita kokoro sukashita you ni
Furidashita amatsubutachi ga
ranhansha kurikaesu
Massugu na hikari ga kousa shite
Yukusaki mo tsugenu mama
dokomademo tsukinukeru
Awai zanzou ryoume ni yakistukete
Kono sora no shita donna toko ni ite mo
Todoku hazu nanda mada minu sekai e
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
Hello, Edward.
You appear to have grown some.
I spoke with Pinako.
- You tried human transmutation.
- [GASP]
What makes you think
you can show up like this?
There's nothing left
for you here anymore!
I noticed.
Tell me, Edward...
what possessed you
to burn down my home?
After what happened
we vowed to never turn back.
- We did it as a symbol of our resolve.
- No you didn't.
- You were hiding the memory.
- [GASP]
You didn't want to be reminded
of what you've done,
and thought you could erase the
memory by destroying the evidence.
You're wrong!
It's just like a child who hides
the sheets after he wets the bed.
You ran away, and you know it.
[SHUDDERING GASP]
I...
You don't know a damn thing!
You make me sick to my stomach.
He's exactly like I was when I was his age.
[DOOR OPENS]
[YOUNG ED AND AL LAUGHING]
[DOOR CLOSES]
[LOW GROWLING]
PINAKO: You haven't changed
in the slightest.
All these years...
and you look exactly the same.
[CHUCKLES]
Where have you been all this time?
Why didn't you come back sooner?
Tricia was waiting for you
until the very end.
- Pinako
- Hm?
The life form my sons transmuted...
- are you positive that it was Tricia?
- Huh?
Well, I wouldn't...
it didn't even look human to me...
- so I wouldn't think of it as—
- No. That's not what I'm asking.
Did you notice the eye color,
or the hair color?
Huh?
What are you trying to get at?
Are you telling me that
that wasn't even Tricia?
For all that those boys sacrificed...
you're saying that thing they created
wasn't even their mother?
LING: Whoa, you don't sleep or eat?
You don't even run out of breath?
AL: Uh-huh, I just have to make
sure the seal doesn't get harmed.
That's so cool!
So you really are immortal then, huh?
- No, I'm not.
-[GASPS]
This body, it's like a time bomb.
Barry mentioned something,
and it made me realize that any type of body
is incompatible with a foreign soul.
Pairing them together,
the body will eventually reject it.
[GASP]
It could happen tomorrow, or ten years
from now, but it's inevitable that it will.
Oh no!
Al, we've got to get you
back in your regular body!
LING: Well, hold on.
If it's about to give out on you...
couldn't you just transfer your soul
into some other object?
Because if that's the case...
then for the time being...
well you're impervious to pain,
and you don't have to eat!
It sounds like a great deal to me!
No it isn't!
You don't know what you're talking about!
Sorry.
Winry?!
[DOOR CLOSES]
[KNOCKING]
AL: Winry?
I'm coming in.
You know, you and brother
always gotta be the first to explode.
I never get the chance
to be the one to get mad.
It's just... Well...
I guess I can't fall asleep.
I don't think this body will let me.
Oh.
Just tell me you're going
to get your body back.
Okay?
[AL GASPS]
ED: Give it back!
You have to give my brother his body back!
He's the only family I have!
I won't let you take it!
Take it?
- [ED GASPS]
- Do you even know what you're saying?
You're the one who tossed his body aside
and put him in that armor.
- Aren't you, Alchemist?
-[ED GASPS]
It's true.
You and I are exactly the same.
Accept it, Edward.
- We make monsters.
[GASP]
[DISORTED VOICE] Edward...
Why did you leave me here like this?
[SHUDDERING GASP]
PINAKO: Ed? Get out of bed already!
Your father's about to head out!
[WHIMPERING]
This one.
Do you mind if I keep it?
It's the only photo we had
taken with all four of us.
Of course. You're welcome to it.
Thank you.
I need to tell you
something important, Pinako.
Huh?
[DOOR OPENS]
Something terrible is going
to happen in this country soon.
You should escape while you can.
[SCOFFS]
This country's lousy with terrible things.
And I can't leave.
I've got other people who need me
here in case they want to come home.
I've given you my warning.
Hey, Hohenheim, wait!
Try not to be such a stranger, all right?
I wish I could, Pinako.
It's too bad I won't get to
enjoy your cooking anymore.
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
You're not really gonna dig it up,
are you, Ed?
[SHOVEL CLANGS, ED GRUNTS]
Why don't we go back?
No.
My stumps are aching from the weather.
It's about to rain.
Let's just hurry and do this.
[ED GAGGING]
Ed!
Don't push yourself.
[SHUDDERING AND GROANING]
Let's head on home.
No.
[SHUDDERS]
I'm not gonna be able to move
forward until I know for sure.
Besides...
You ran away.
I won't run away from this.
[SHOVEL HITS BONE]
[GASPS]
Granny...
Mom's hair was a light chestnut color...
This is black.
This femur, it's much too long.
And this pelvis, I'm pretty sure it's male.
It is?
I'm sorry, but I'm afraid
this isn't your mother, Ed.
[ED WHIMPERS]
[LAUGHING]
And that's it.
It really is impossible to
bring the dead back to life.
The undeniable truth.
[LAUGHS]
It was impossible all along
Edward, now listen to me.
You've gotta get a hold of yourself.
[SIGH]
I'm okay, Granny. It's okay.
From the moment I made this
thing, it's been a symbol of my despair.
But not anymore.
Now it's an emblem of hope.
Al can be returned to normal!
Fullmetal Alchemist.
[PHONE RINGING]
Curtis residence.
I didn't expect this.
You never call.
Uh, yeah.
I need to ask you something, teacher.
But, well...
Well what?
Spit it out.
It has to do with when you
tried to transmute your baby.
[GASP]
What about it, Ed?
The thing is... What Al and I transmuted...
It wasn't actually our mother.
What is this, Ed?
What are you trying to tell me?
I'm sorry to ask you this,
but the child you transmuted...
Are you sure that it was your
child that you brought back?
[GASP]
[PHONE HANGS UP]
PINAKO: Thank you, Ed.
It's good to know my son
and his wife helped people.
I'm proud of them.
So Hohenheim...
Did he even bother to say where he was going?
Of course he didn't.
And I didn't a—
Ahh!
What's wrong with me?
I can't believe I forgot
to give him the message!
A message?
Yes.
A last request...
From your mother.
I'll be gone when he returns.
Can you tell him something?
I need him to know... I
couldn't keep my promise.
I died before he did.
And I'm so sorry.
Promise?
What promise?
You got me.
Sorry to ask, but could you
pass it on if you bump into him?
Why should I have to?
I know it doesn't seem like it,
but he does care about you and your brother.
[LAUGHS]
Yeah, I'll pass it on right
after I clock him in the face.
[TRAIN HORN]
Heading back to Central
already, are you?
Yeah. Al's probably mad at me.
I'm gonna have plenty of explaining to do.
What the hell?!
I'm sorry, brother!
Wha—how are you this beat up?!
And you!
What the hell are you doing here?!
Eating a delicious dinner.
[DOOR OPENS]
Seriously!
How did this happen to you?!
Uh...
ED: A Homunculus
and Barry the Chopper...
And just to throw a cherry on top,
you find out your body might reject your soul.
I'm gonna have to extend what
little you have left of your armor.
[SIGHS]
Ed, he'll be able to get
his body back, right?
Yeah, of course he will.
I told you I'm gonna get it back.
Al...
I've gotta tell you something.
I dug up the body that we
transmuted in Resembool.
[AL GASPS]
What?!
Why would you do that?!
Because, Al...
I found out that the thing we buried
wasn't really our mother.
[GASP]
But... Hold on a minute.
The thing we made?
Then that means...
I don't know what,
but it was something completely different.
But if it wasn't, then what happened to me?
That's just it.
This has actually convinced
me we can return you to normal.
[AL GASPS]
Ed, are you sure?
Yeah.
But before I start explaining how...
Well, uh, Winry... Do, um... Uh...
Do you remember when Al and I got in a fight
when we were kids about...
Who'd marry you?
Huh?
The fight we were
talking about on the roof?
Yeah, that one.
Al told me you turned him down.
Mm-hmm.
Turned you both down.
Whatever.
So the question's for both of you, then.
What was your reasoning?
She said...
[BOTH]: "I just don't like
men who are shorter than me."
[ED SCREAMS]
You can't judge a man
for something he can't help!
WINRY: Uh...
ED: [WAILING]
WINRY: I don't really see how this has anything to do with getting Al's body back.
ED: [CONTINUES WAILING]
I had to be sure.
Al had a memory of
something I don't recall.
And you seem to clearly
remember it the same way, Winry.
Which means that it
happened without a doubt.
So now that we know you
remembered something real,
then we also know for a fact
that really is Al bonded in there.
I pulled you out, Al.
I actually did it.
I know it was only your
soul, but that's just it...
If I was able to pull that much of you out,
then I've got a hunch that your body's
still in there, and I can pull it out.
You think my body's still in the portal?
Existing separately from my soul?
[GASPS] Like Barry's body!
Right. What did you see?
Try to think back.
Can you remember what happened
when the truth unraveled you?
I reached out...
And it was me.
It was my hand I grabbed!
I knew it.
Doesn't look like we're
done with the truth yet, Al.
We're gonna get in there
and pull your body out.
Brother...
AL: After the portal, I remember
looking at you from inside that thing...
The thing we thought was Mom.
You were inside of it?
That thing was you?
AL: I guess so.
But my soul didn't bind.
It must have rejected me right away.
So that means...
We didn't harm
anyone else's soul after all.
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
[ED AND AL GASP]
Mr. Elric? You have
a telephone call from Izumi Curtis.
IZUMI: I did some research.
Sig and I looked up our family lines,
and well...
The child that I transmuted... It couldn't...
It didn't have a single physical trait
that could have come from us.
You're onto something, aren't you?
Yes.
I've come to the conclusion
that death is permanent.
So not even transmutation
can change that fact.
All this time...
I thought that I must have missed something.
But it was impossible
to do in the first place.
Ed.
Yes, ma'am?!
Thank you.
[LINE DISCONNECTS]
AL: So what did Teacher have to say?
Well, I'm not really sure why, but she said...
Thank you.
Al...?
This entire time, I've been
blaming myself for what happened.
I thought it was me.
I thought I was the one who
killed Mom a second time.
And so did I, Al.
Thanks, brother. Thank you.
I wasn't the one who killed Mom after all.
Izumi...
I feel like I've been brought back to life.
Our child wasn't made to
suffer twice because of me.
ED: But still...
None of this changes the fact
that I'm the one who put you in that body.
And I don't care what it takes.
I'm gonna make you normal again—
Brother!
I was right there with you,
and I knew that there were risks.
So quit trying to shoulder
all of this on your own.
I can't watch you suffer like this.
Not on your own.
I can't just stand back and watch
other people get hurt over what I've done.
Like what happened to Mr. Hughes.
I felt like it was my fault
when I found out he was dead.
And I told myself that
if it meant other people getting hurt
then I don't even want my body back.
Brother...
I've met other people
who weren't exactly human.
But they still managed to
live their lives with a purpose.
And even in this body...
it hasn't stopped other people
from treating me like I'm still human.
This body could reject me any time.
But it's the same with being human.
You never know when you
might get sick or die in an accident.
So I can still get by like this.
I can live a somewhat normal life.
And that's how I've managed to keep going.
But now...
I can't take it anymore!
Because... I can't...
I can't take all the nights by myself!
It's too lonely.
And that's why I have
to get back to normal.
Sure. And you're going to.
[CLANG]
We'll knock that truth jerk on his butt.
And then we're gonna pull
your body right out of that place.
AL: Yeah!
WINRY: Huh?
That's weird.
Have his shoulders always been so broad?
Let it all out, let it all out
Tsuyogaranakute ii n da ne
Dareka ga kaite'tta
Kabe no rakugaki no hana ga yureru
Jibunrashisa nante, dare mo wakaranai yo
Nagai nagai michi no tochuu
de nakushitari, hirottari,
Kyuu ni samishiku natte,
naichau hi mo aru kedo
Namida mo itami mo, hoshi ni kaeyou
Ashita wo terasu akari wo tomosou
Chiisana te kazashite
futari de tsukurou hoshikuzu wo
Tsuyoku hikaru ein wo
Sayonara itsuka wa kuru ka mo shirenu
Kisetsu wa sore demo meguri megutte'ku
Chiisaku mayotte mo aruite'ku
Kimi to aruite'ku
Sore daku wa kawaranaide iyou ne
The meer sight of his injured friend hastens the Colonel's
determination to uncover the forces plaguing the military.
While the young man is forced to
put everything he has on the line
In order to escape from a dead end.
Next time on Fullmetal Alchemist: Brotherhood
Episode 21: Advance of the Fool
Never wait for the battle to come to you.
Strike the first blow.